<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>
<chapter id="event-handling">
  <title>Event handling in GTK+ 3</title>

  <para>
    In version 3.6, GTK+ has overhauled the way widgets handle input events
    considerably. The main motivation for this has been the more complex
    interaction models used by modern toolkitts. In particular, enabling
    all the behaviors people expect from multitouch support was guiding the
    design.
  </para>

  <para>
    The principles outlined in this chapter are only relevant for people
    that want to implement their own #GtkWidgets. It is not necessary that
    you understand the concepts here when all you want to do is use existing
    widgets to create your own application.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>The high-level view</title>

    <para>
      FIXME
    </para>

    <para>
      The GTK event system is a cooperative event handling system. This means
      that event recognizers need not know on their own if they should
      recognize an event, but they communicate with other recognizers about
      the process.
    </para>
  </section>


  <section>
  <title>Setting up your widget</title>

  <section>
    <title>Using GtkBuilder</title>
    <para>
      FIXME (with examples!)
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Manual addition of event recognizers</title>
    <para>
      FIXME (with examples!)
    </para>
  </section>

  </section>


  <section>
  <title>Event flow</title>

  <section>
    <title>Lifetime of a #GtkEventTracker</title>
    <para>
      FIXME
    </para>
  <section>

  <section>
    <title>Flow of a #GdkEvent through the event machinery</title>
    <para>
      FIXME (make sure to not be too specific, so we can still change stuff later)
    </para>
  <section>

  </section>


  <section>
  <title>Writing your own event recognizers</title>

  <para>
    The GTK developers generally discourage the writing of new event recognizers.
    We are trying to provide a consistent feel to GTK applications and with all
    the included event recognizers we think almost all the functionality needed
    for event handling should be there for you to use.

    Of course, every rule has its exceptions or you might just feel adventurous.
    so should you see yourself in a situation where you need to write your own
    event recognizers, here are some hints on how to do it.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>FIXME</title>
    <para>
      FIXME
    </para>
  <section>

  </section>

</chapter>
