<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="gtk-getting-started" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  <title>Getting Started with GTK+</title>

  <para>This chapter contains some tutorial information to get you
  started with GTK+ programming. It assumes that you have GTK+, its
  dependencies and a C compiler installed and ready to use. If you
  need to build GTK+ itself first, refer to the
  <link linkend="gtk-compiling">Compiling the GTK+ libraries</link>
  section in this reference.</para>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Basics</title>

    <para>To begin our introduction to GTK, we'll start with the simplest
    program possible. This program will create an empty 200x200 pixel
    window:</para>

    <para>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="window-default.png" format="PNG"></inlinegraphic>
    </para>

    <informalexample><programlisting>
      <xi:include href="../../../../examples/window-default.c" parse="text">
        <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </programlisting></informalexample>

    <para>You can compile the program above with GCC using:</para>

    <para><literallayout>
      <literal>gcc `pkg-config --cflags gtk+-3.0` -o window-default window-default.c `pkg-config --libs gtk+-3.0`</literal>
    </literallayout></para>

    <note><para>For more information on how to compile a GTK+ application, please
    refer to the <link linkend="gtk-compiling">Compiling GTK+ Applications</link>
    section in this reference.</para></note>

    <para>All GTK+ applications will, of course, include
    <filename>gtk/gtk.h</filename>, which declares functions, types and
    macros required by GTK+ applications.</para>

    <warning><para>Even if GTK+ installs multiple header files, only the
    top-level <filename>gtk/gtk.h</filename> header can be directly included
    by third party code. The compiler will abort with an error if any other
    header is directly included.</para></warning>

    <para>We then proceed into the <function>main</function>() function of the
    application, and we declare a <varname>window</varname> variable as a pointer
    of type #GtkWidget.</para>

    <para>The following line will call gtk_init(), which
    is the initialization function for GTK+; this function will set up GTK+,
    the type system, the connection to the windowing environment, etc. The
    gtk_init() takes as arguments the pointers to the command line arguments
    counter and string array; this allows GTK+ to parse specific command line
    arguments that control the behavior of GTK+ itself. The parsed arguments
    will be removed from the array, leaving the unrecognized ones for your
    application to parse.</para>

    <note><para>For more information on which command line arguments GTK+
    recognizes, please refer to the <link linkend="gtk-running">Running GTK+
    Applications</link> section in this reference.</para></note>

    <para>The call to gtk_window_new() will create a new #GtkWindow and store
    it inside the <varname>window</varname> variable. The type of the window
    is %GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL, which means that the #GtkWindow will be managed
    by the windowing system: it will have a frame, a title bar and window
    controls, depending on the platform.</para>

    <para>In order to terminate the application when the #GtkWindow is
    destroyed, we connect the #GtkWidget::destroy signal to the gtk_main_quit()
    function. This function will terminate the GTK+ main loop started by calling
    gtk_main() later. The #GtkWidget::destroy signal is emitted when a widget is
    destroyed, either by explicitly calling gtk_widget_destroy() or when the
    widget is unparented. Top-level #GtkWindow<!-- -->s are also destroyed when
    the Close window control button is clicked.</para>

    <para>#GtkWidget<!-- -->s are hidden by default. By calling gtk_widget_show()
    on a #GtkWidget we are asking GTK+ to set the visibility attribute so that it
    can be displayed. All this work is done after the main loop has been
    started.</para>

    <para>The last line of interest is the call to gtk_main(). This function will
    start the GTK+ main loop and will block the control flow of the
    main() until the gtk_main_quit() function is called.</para>

    <para>While the program is running, GTK+ is receiving
    <firstterm>events</firstterm>. These are typically input events caused by
    the user interacting with your program, but also things like messages from
    the window manager or other applications. GTK+ processes these and as a
    result, <firstterm>signals</firstterm> may be emitted on your widgets.
    Connecting handlers for these signals is how you normally make your
    program do something in response to user input.</para>

    <para>The following example is slightly more complex, and tries to
    showcase some of the capabilities of GTK+.</para>

    <para>In the long tradition of programming languages and libraries,
    it is called <emphasis>Hello, World</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="hello-world.png" format="PNG"></inlinegraphic>
    </para>

    <example id="gtk-getting-started-hello-world">
      <title>Hello World in GTK+</title>
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="../../../../examples/hello-world.c" parse="text">
          <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Packing</title>

    <para>When creating an application, you'll want to put more than one widget
    inside a window. Our first helloworld example only used one widget so we
    could simply use a gtk_container_add() call to "pack" the widget into the
    window. But when you want to put more than one widget into a window, it
    it becomes important to control how each widget is positioned and sized.
    This is where packing comes in.</para>

    <para>GTK+ comes with a large variety of <firstterm>layout containers</firstterm>
    whose purpose it is to control the layout of the child widgets that are
    added to them. See <xref linkend="LayoutContainers"/> for an overview.</para>

    <para>The following example shows how the GtkGrid container lets you
    arrange several buttons:</para>

    <para>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="grid-packing.png" format="PNG"></inlinegraphic>
    </para>

    <example id="gtk-getting-started-grid-packing">
      <title>Packing buttons</title>
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="../../../../examples/grid-packing.c" parse="text">
          <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Drawing</title>

    <para>Many widgets, like buttons, do all their drawing themselves. You
    just tell them the label you want to see, and they figure out what font
    to use, draw the button outline and focus rectangle, etc. Sometimes, it
    is necessary to do some custom drawing. In that case, a #GtkDrawingArea
    might be the right widget to use. It offers a canvas on which you can
    draw by connecting to the #GtkWidget::draw signal.
    </para>

    <para>The contents of a widget often need to be partially or fully redrawn,
    e.g. when another window is moved and uncovers part of the widget, or
    when tie window containing it is resized. It is also possible to explicitly
    cause part or all of the widget to be redrawn, by calling
    gtk_widget_queue_draw() or its variants. GTK+ takes care of most of the
    details by providing a ready-to-use cairo context to the ::draw signal
    handler.</para>

    <para>The following example shows a ::draw signal handler. It is a bit
    more complicated than the previous examples, since it also demonstrates
    input event handling by means of ::button-press and ::motion-notify
    handlers.</para>

    <para>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="drawing.png" format="PNG"></inlinegraphic>
    </para>

    <example id="gtk-getting-started-drawing">
      <title>Drawing in response to input</title>
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="../../../../examples/drawing.c" parse="text">
          <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Building interfaces</title>

    <para>When construcing a more complicated user interface, with dozens
    or hundreds of widgets, doing all the setup work in C code is
    cumbersome, and making changes becomes next to impossible.</para>

    <para>Thankfully, GTK+ supports the separation of user interface
    layout from your business logic, by using UI descriptions in an
    XML format that can be parsed by the #GtkBuilder class.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Packing buttons with GtkBuilder</title>
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="../../../../examples/builder.c" parse="text">
          <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
      </programlisting>
      The builder.ui file looks like this:
      <programlisting>
        <xi:include href="../../../../examples/builder.ui" parse="text">
          <xi:fallback>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Note that GtkBuilder can also be used to construct objects
    that are not widgets, such as tree models, adjustments, etc.
    That is the reason the method we use here is called
    gtk_builder_get_object() and returns a GObject* instead of a
    GtkWidget*.</para>

    <para>Normally, you would pass a full path to
    gtk_builder_add_from_file() to make the execution of your program
    independent of the current directory. A common location to install
    UI descriptions and similar data is
    <filename>/usr/share/<replaceable>appname</replaceable></filename>.
    </para>

    <para>It is also possible to embed the UI description in the source
    code as a string and use gtk_builder_add_from_string() to load it.
    But keeping the UI description in a separate file has several
    advantages: It is then possible to make minor adjustments to the UI
    without recompiling your program, and, more importantly, graphical
    UI editors such as <ulink url="http://glade.gnome.org">glade</ulink>
    can load the file and allow you to create and modify your UI by
    point-and-click.</para>

  </simplesect>
</chapter>
