<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE partintro PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
               ]>
<partintro>
<para>
GTK+ is a library for creating graphical user interfaces. It
works on many UNIX-like platforms, Windows, and OS X.
GTK+ is released under the GNU Library General Public License
(GNU LGPL), which allows for flexible licensing of client
applications. GTK+ has a C-based object-oriented architecture that
allows for maximum flexibility.  Bindings for many other languages have
been written, including C++, Objective-C, Guile/Scheme, Perl, Python,
TOM, Ada95, Free Pascal, and Eiffel.
</para>
<para>
GTK+ depends on the following libraries:
<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term>GLib</term>
<listitem><para>
A general-purpose utility library, not specific to graphical user interfaces.
GLib provides many useful data types, macros, type conversions,
string utilities, file utilities, a main loop abstraction, and so on.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>GObject</term>
<listitem><para>A library that provides a type system, a collection of
fundamental types including an object type, a signal system.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>GIO</term>
<listitem><para>A modern, easy-to-use VFS API including abstractions for
files, drives, volumes, stream IO, as well as network programming and
DBus communication.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>cairo</term>
<listitem><para>Cairo is a 2D graphics library with support for multiple
output devices.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Pango</term>
<listitem><para>
Pango is a library for internationalized text handling. It centers
around the PangoLayout object, representing a paragraph of text.
Pango provides the engine for GtkTextView, GtkLabel, GtkEntry, and
other widgets that display text.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ATK</term>
<listitem><para>
ATK is the Accessibility Toolkit. It provides a set of generic
interfaces allowing accessibility technologies to interact with a
graphical user interface. For example, a screen reader uses ATK to
discover the text in an interface and read it to blind users.  GTK+
widgets have built-in support for accessibility using the ATK
framework.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>GdkPixbuf</term>
<listitem><para>
This is a small library which allows you to create GdkPixbuf
("pixel buffer") objects from image data or image files.
Use a GdkPixbuf in combination with GtkImage to display images.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>GDK</term>
<listitem><para>
GDK is the abstraction layer that allows GTK+ to support multiple
windowing systems. GDK provides window system facilities on X11, Windows,
and OS X.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>GTK+</term>
<listitem><para>
The GTK+ library itself contains <firstterm>widgets</firstterm>,
that is, GUI components such as GtkButton or GtkTextView.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</partintro>
