<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xdg_shell">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2008-2013 Kristian Høgsberg
    Copyright © 2013      Rafael Antognolli
    Copyright © 2013      Jasper St. Pierre
    Copyright © 2010-2013 Intel Corporation

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="xdg_shell" version="1">
    <description summary="create desktop-style surfaces">
      This interface is implemented by servers that provide
      desktop-style user interfaces.

      It allows clients to associate a xdg_surface with
      a basic surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="version">
      <description summary="latest protocol version">
	Use this enum to check the protocol version, and it will be updated
	automatically.
      </description>
      <entry name="current" value="2" summary="Always the latest version"/>
    </enum>


    <request name="use_unstable_version">
      <description summary="enable use of this unstable version">
	Use this request in order to enable use of this interface.

	Understand and agree that one is using an unstable interface,
	that will likely change in the future, breaking the API.
      </description>
      <arg name="version" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xdg_surface">
      <description summary="create a shell surface from a surface">
	Create a shell surface for an existing surface.

	Only one shell or popup surface can be associated with a given
	surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_surface"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xdg_popup">
      <description summary="create a shell surface from a surface">
	Create a popup surface for an existing surface.

	Only one shell or popup surface can be associated with a given
	surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_popup"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="parent" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat whose pointer is used"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the implicit grab on the pointer"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="flags" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <event name="ping">
      <description summary="check if the client is alive">
        The ping event asks the client if it's still alive. Pass the
        serial specified in the event back to the compositor by sending
        a "pong" request back with the specified serial.

        Compositors can use this to determine if the client is still
        alive. It's unspecified what will happen if the client doesn't
        respond to the ping request, or in what timeframe. Clients should
        try to respond in a reasonable amount of time.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="pass this to the callback"/>
    </event>

    <request name="pong">
      <description summary="respond to a ping event">
	A client must respond to a ping event with a pong request or
	the client may be deemed unresponsive.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the ping event"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_surface" version="1">

    <description summary="desktop-style metadata interface">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface, for
      implementations that provide a desktop-style user interface.

      It provides requests to treat surfaces like windows, allowing to set
      properties like maximized, fullscreen, minimized, and to move and resize
      them, and associate metadata like title and app id.

      On the server side the object is automatically destroyed when
      the related wl_surface is destroyed.  On client side,
      xdg_surface.destroy() must be called before destroying
      the wl_surface object.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="remove xdg_surface interface">
	The xdg_surface interface is removed from the wl_surface object
	that was turned into a xdg_surface with
	xdg_shell.get_xdg_surface request. The xdg_surface properties,
	like maximized and fullscreen, are lost. The wl_surface loses
	its role as a xdg_surface. The wl_surface is unmapped.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_transient_for">
      <description summary="surface is a child of another surface">
	Setting a surface as transient of another means that it is child
	of another surface.

	Child surfaces are stacked above their parents, and will be
	unmapped if the parent is unmapped too. They should not appear
	on task bars and alt+tab.
      </description>
      <arg name="parent" type="object" interface="wl_surface" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_margin">
      <description summary="set the visible frame boundaries">
        This tells the compositor what the visible size of the window
        should be, so it can use it to determine what borders to use for
        constrainment and alignment.

        CSD often has invisible areas for decoration purposes, like drop
        shadows. These "shadow" drawings need to be subtracted out of the
        normal boundaries of the window when computing where to place
        windows (e.g. to set this window so it's centered on top of another,
        or to put it to the left or right of the screen.)

        This value should change as little as possible at runtime, to
        prevent flicker.

        This value is also ignored when the window is maximized or
        fullscreen, and assumed to be 0.

        If never called, this value is assumed to be 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="left_margin" type="int"/>
      <arg name="right_margin" type="int"/>
      <arg name="top_margin" type="int"/>
      <arg name="bottom_margin" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_title">
      <description summary="set surface title">
	Set a short title for the surface.

	This string may be used to identify the surface in a task bar,
	window list, or other user interface elements provided by the
	compositor.

	The string must be encoded in UTF-8.
      </description>
      <arg name="title" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_app_id">
      <description summary="set surface class">
	Set an id for the surface.

	The app id identifies the general class of applications to which
	the surface belongs.

	It should be the ID that appears in the new desktop entry
	specification, the interface name.
      </description>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="move">
      <description summary="start an interactive move">
	Start a pointer-driven move of the surface.

	This request must be used in response to a button press event.
	The server may ignore move requests depending on the state of
	the surface (e.g. fullscreen or maximized).
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat whose pointer is used"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the implicit grab on the pointer"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="resize_edge">
      <description summary="edge values for resizing">
	These values are used to indicate which edge of a surface
	is being dragged in a resize operation. The server may
	use this information to adapt its behavior, e.g. choose
	an appropriate cursor image.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0"/>
      <entry name="top" value="1"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2"/>
      <entry name="left" value="4"/>
      <entry name="top_left" value="5"/>
      <entry name="bottom_left" value="6"/>
      <entry name="right" value="8"/>
      <entry name="top_right" value="9"/>
      <entry name="bottom_right" value="10"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="resize">
      <description summary="start an interactive resize">
	Start a pointer-driven resizing of the surface.

	This request must be used in response to a button press event.
	The server may ignore resize requests depending on the state of
	the surface (e.g. fullscreen or maximized).
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat whose pointer is used"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the implicit grab on the pointer"/>
      <arg name="edges" type="uint" summary="which edge or corner is being dragged"/>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="suggest resize">
	The configure event asks the client to resize its surface.

	The size is a hint, in the sense that the client is free to
	ignore it if it doesn't resize, pick a smaller size (to
	satisfy aspect ratio or resize in steps of NxM pixels).

	The edges parameter provides a hint about how the surface
	was resized. The client may use this information to decide
	how to adjust its content to the new size (e.g. a scrolling
	area might adjust its content position to leave the viewable
	content unmoved). Valid edge values are from resize_edge enum.

	The client is free to dismiss all but the last configure
	event it received.

	The width and height arguments specify the size of the window
	in surface local coordinates.
      </description>

      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <request name="set_output">
      <description summary="set the default output used by this surface">
	Set the default output used by this surface when it is first mapped.

	If this value is NULL (default), it's up to the compositor to choose
	which display will be used to map this surface.

	When fullscreen or maximized state are set on this surface, and it
	wasn't mapped yet, the output set with this method will be used.
	Otherwise, the output where the surface is currently mapped will be
	used.
      </description>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>

    <event name="request_set_fullscreen">
      <description summary="server requests that the client set fullscreen">
	Event sent from the compositor to the client requesting that the client
	goes to a fullscreen state. It's the client job to call set_fullscreen
	and really trigger the fullscreen state.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="request_unset_fullscreen">
      <description summary="server requests that the client unset fullscreen">
	Event sent from the compositor to the client requesting that the client
	leaves the fullscreen state. It's the client job to call
	unset_fullscreen and really leave the fullscreen state.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="set_fullscreen">
      <description summary="set the surface state as fullscreen">
	Set the surface as fullscreen.

	After this request, the compositor should send a configure event
	informing the output size.

	This request informs the compositor that the next attached buffer
	committed will be in a fullscreen state. The buffer size should be the
	same size as the size informed in the configure event, if the client
	doesn't want to leave any empty area.

	In other words: the next attached buffer after set_maximized is the new
	maximized buffer. And the surface will be positioned at the maximized
	position on commit.

	A simple way to synchronize and wait for the correct configure event is
	to use a wl_display.sync request right after the set_fullscreen
	request. When the sync callback returns, the last configure event
	received just before it will be the correct one, and should contain the
	right size for the surface to maximize.

	Setting one state won't unset another state. Use
	xdg_surface.unset_fullscreen for unsetting it.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_fullscreen">
      <description summary="unset the surface state as fullscreen">
	Unset the surface fullscreen state.

	Same negotiation as set_fullscreen must be used.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="request_set_maximized">
      <description summary="server requests that the client set maximized">
	Event sent from the compositor to the client requesting that the client
	goes to a maximized state. It's the client job to call set_maximized
	and really trigger the maximized state.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="request_unset_maximized">
      <description summary="server requests that the client unset maximized">
	Event sent from the compositor to the client requesting that the client
	leaves the maximized state. It's the client job to call unset_maximized
	and really leave the maximized state.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="set_maximized">
      <description summary="set the surface state as maximized">
	Set the surface as maximized.

	After this request, the compositor will send a configure event
	informing the output size minus panel and other MW decorations.

	This request informs the compositor that the next attached buffer
	committed will be in a maximized state. The buffer size should be the
	same size as the size informed in the configure event, if the client
	doesn't want to leave any empty area.

	In other words: the next attached buffer after set_maximized is the new
	maximized buffer. And the surface will be positioned at the maximized
	position on commit.

	A simple way to synchronize and wait for the correct configure event is
	to use a wl_display.sync request right after the set_maximized request.
	When the sync callback returns, the last configure event received just
	before it will be the correct one, and should contain the right size
	for the surface to maximize.

	Setting one state won't unset another state. Use
	xdg_surface.unset_maximized for unsetting it.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_maximized">
      <description summary="unset the surface state as maximized">
	Unset the surface maximized state.

	Same negotiation as set_maximized must be used.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_minimized">
      <description summary="set the surface state as minimized">
	Set the surface minimized state.

	Setting one state won't unset another state.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="focused_set">
      <description summary="surface was focused">
	The focused_set event is sent when this surface has been
	activated. Window decorations should be updated accordingly.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="focused_unset">
      <description summary="surface was unfocused">
	The focused_unset event is sent when this surface has been
	deactivated, because another surface has been activated. Window
	decorations should be updated accordingly.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="delete">
      <description summary="surface wants to be closed">
        The delete event is sent by the compositor when the user
        wants the surface to be closed. This should be equivalent to
        the user clicking the close button in client-side decorations,
        if your application has any...

        This is only a request that the user intends to close your
        window. The client may choose to ignore this request, or show
        a dialog to ask the user to save their data...
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_popup" version="1">
    <description summary="desktop-style metadata interface">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface, for
      implementations that provide a desktop-style popups/menus. A popup
      surface is a transient surface with an added pointer grab.

      An existing implicit grab will be changed to owner-events mode,
      and the popup grab will continue after the implicit grab ends
      (i.e. releasing the mouse button does not cause the popup to be
      unmapped).

      The popup grab continues until the window is destroyed or a mouse
      button is pressed in any other clients window. A click in any of
      the clients surfaces is reported as normal, however, clicks in
      other clients surfaces will be discarded and trigger the callback.

      The x and y arguments specify the locations of the upper left
      corner of the surface relative to the upper left corner of the
      parent surface, in surface local coordinates.

      xdg_popup surfaces are always transient for another surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="remove xdg_surface interface">
	The xdg_surface interface is removed from the wl_surface object
	that was turned into a xdg_surface with
	xdg_shell.get_xdg_surface request. The xdg_surface properties,
	like maximized and fullscreen, are lost. The wl_surface loses
	its role as a xdg_surface. The wl_surface is unmapped.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="popup_done">
      <description summary="popup interaction is done">
	The popup_done event is sent out when a popup grab is broken,
	that is, when the users clicks a surface that doesn't belong
	to the client owning the popup surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the implicit grab on the pointer"/>
    </event>

  </interface>
</protocol>
